<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook" />
<updated>2016-05-22T23:58:42-06:00</updated>
<id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/</id>
<author>
  <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
  <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/</uri>
  
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Giroux, Henry. &ldquo;Schooling and the Culture of Positivism: Notes on the Death of History.&rdquo; 1979/2014.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/giroux-schooling-and-the-culture-of-positivism/" />
  <id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/giroux-schooling-and-the-culture-of-positivism</id>
  <published>2016-05-18T20:35:21-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-18T20:35:21-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
    <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;This post from my regular blog seems worth bringing over here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/694396588&quot;&gt;Worldcat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the holidays I read Giroux’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/694396588&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Critical Pedagogy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of some older and new essays. The one that particularly sticks with me is “Schooling and the Culture of Positivism: Notes on the Death of History.” It’s a bummer that he hasn’t figured out a way to make this open access. If you can get ahold of it—perhaps you have access to the &lt;em&gt;Educational Theory&lt;/em&gt; journal or can get &lt;em&gt;On Critical Pedagogy&lt;/em&gt; through ILL—I definitely recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the essays in this volume, this might have the most relevance for librarianship / archivists / LIS / etc., for it deals at length with the myth of “neutrality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay links the ways that history is taught with ways that produce “common sense” understandings of the world—a production of a particular, politically-inflected common sense that Antonio Gramsci terms “ideological &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarblogs.emory.edu/postcolonialstudies/2014/06/20/hegemony-in-gramsci/&quot;&gt;hegemony&lt;/a&gt;,” which legitimizes the present distributions of power while attempting to foreclose thoughts that the world should be otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giroux is careful to clarify that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Culture of positivism,” in this context, is used to make a distinction between a specific philosophic movement and &lt;em&gt;a form&lt;/em&gt; of cultural hegemony. The distinction is important because it shifts the focus of debate about the tenets of positivism from the terrain of philosophy to the field of ideology. […Furthermore…] the culture of positivism undermines any viable notion of critical historical consciousness. (p. 25)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among its other insights, this essay helps articulate the difference between certain types of theory and what I consider properly &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt; theory. Theory in the culture of positivism attempts primarily to refine methods and attempts to limit “knowledge” to only things that are value-free. On the other hand, Giroux reminds us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In classical thought, theory was seen as a way men could free themselves from dogma and opinions in order to provide an orientation for ethical action. In other words, theory was viewed as an extension of ethics and was linked to the search for truth and justice. The prevailing positivist consciousness has forgotten the function that theory once served. Under the prevailing dominant ideology, theory has been stripped of its concern with ends and ethics, and “appears unable to free itself from the ends set and given to science by the pre-given empirical reality.” (p. 26)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believing that this sort of research and education has successfully evacuated itself of history and values, however, comes with the cost of not recognizing or contending with the socially-embedded foundation of its own pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giroux again distinguishes between “objectivity” and “objectivism”—both of which promote rationality and minimize bias, but only one of which can reflect on its own uses and outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Missing from this form of educational rationality is the complex interplay among knowledge, power, and ideology. The sources of this failing can be traced to the confusion between objectivity and objectivism, a confusion which once lays bare the conservative ideological underpinnings of the positivist educational paradigm. If objectivity in classroom teaching refers to the attempt to be scrupulously careful about minimizing biases, false beliefs, and discriminating behavior in rationalizing and developing pedagogical thought and practice, then this is a laudable notion that should govern our work. By contrast, objectivism refers to an orientation that is atemporal and ahistorical in nature. In this orientation, “fact” becomes the foundation for all forms of knowledge, and values and intentionality lose their political potency by being abstracted from the notion of meaning. When objectivism replaces objectivity, as Bernstein points out, “is not an innocent mistaken epistemological doctrine.” It becomes a potent form of ideology that smothers the tug of conscience and blinds its adherents to the ideological nature of their own frame of reference. (p. 34)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of reflection about outcomes and ways of being embedded within societal structures is not only a false claim to neutrality, it leaves educators unwilling to consider how they might be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inthelibrarywiththeleadpipe.org/2014/locating-the-library-in-institutional-oppression/&quot;&gt;located in institutional oppression&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:unable&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:unable&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Objectivism suggests more than a false expression of neutrality. In essence, it tacitly represents a denial of ethical values. Its commitment to rigorous techniques, mathematical expression, and law-like regularities supports not only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; form of scientific inquiry but social formations that are inherently repressive and elitist as well. Its elimination of “ideology” works in the service of the ideology of social engineers. By denying the relevance of certain norms in guiding and shaping how we ought to live with each other, it tacitly supports principles of hierarchy and control. Built into its objective quest for certainty is not simply the elimination of intellectual and valuative conflict, but the suppression of free will, intentionality, and collective struggle. Clearly, such interests can move beyond the culture of positivism only to the degree that they are able to make a distinction between emancipatory political practice and technological administrative control. (p. 35)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wending its way around to discussing how false neutrality promotes social control rather than liberation reminds me of another excellent—and sadly also not open access—essay, Christine Pawley’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/602955&quot;&gt;“Hegemony’s Handmaid? The Library and Information Studies Curriculum from a Class Perspective”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a reading on library values, hegemony, and what claims of neutrality promote, Giroux’s essay provides a lot to think through! I can only hope that as LIS seems to continue moving from “library studies” and towards calling ourselves library science, information science, and operating with metrics, we recognize that these cannot operate without social values and ethics. If we do not make these values explicit objects of intentional reflection, we run the risk of implicitly accepting the larger social structures around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:unable&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Indeed, the situation goes beyond individual predisposition or “will.” By structuring professional education rhetoric away from considering the complexities of values and toward technical certainty, a self-congratulatory belief in neutrality steers journals and publishers away from publishing works that prioritize considerations of ethics or how the present configuration came to be. It therefore leaves individuals wary of attempting research on values or history, for these imperil their ability to publish and thereby make a solid case for tenure. In other words, to the extent that this false neutrality afflicts education and related disciplines such as LIS, it goes beyond individual will and instead materially structures the professional literature, the professoriate, other administrators, and the institutions’ practices. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:unable&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/giroux-schooling-and-the-culture-of-positivism/&quot;&gt;Giroux, Henry. &amp;ldquo;Schooling and the Culture of Positivism: Notes on the Death of History.&amp;rdquo; 1979/2014.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Ryan P. Randall at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook&quot;&gt;Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook&lt;/a&gt; on May 18, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Burt, Laura. &ldquo;Vivian Harsh Adult Ed Library's Role as Community Center.&rdquo; 2009.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/burt-vivian-harsh-adult-ed-librarys-role-as-community-center-2009/" />
  <id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/burt-vivian-harsh-adult-ed-librarys-role-as-community-center-2009</id>
  <published>2016-05-14T22:23:38-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-14T22:23:38-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
    <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Burt, Laura. “Vivian Harsh, Adult Education, and the Library’s Role as Community Center.” &lt;em&gt;Libraries &amp;amp; the Cultural Record&lt;/em&gt; 44.2 (2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link (paywall):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/5547063193&quot;&gt;WorldCat&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/25549550&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Libraries &amp;amp; the Cultural Record&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vivian G. Harsh, director of George Cleveland Hall Branch Library from 1932 to 1958, part of the Chicago Public Library in the Bronzeville neighborhood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special Research Collection about African American life, history, and culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book Review and Lecture Forum (author calls it “pivotal” in intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;known her “knowledge of all things African and African American”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rich collection of African American resources (234)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She made the Hall a “vital community center.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The library regularly sponsored debates and lectures on topics important to her patrons, such as African American politics and history. Patrons were encouraged and enabled to debate, question, and process as a community issues such as democracy, World War II, and global politics. Her work to create a {==234/235==} safe space for community intellectual inquiry was vital, as debate over questions such as the rights of African Americans at that time could be regarded as dangerous, especially for her African American patrons. Harsh helped preserve and teach the cultural history of African Americans and Africans, vital to the identity of her neighborhood, and encouraged the development of a sense of community and trust in the library as an intellectual center. Her work left a lasting impact not only on her collection but also on her patrons. (234-5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emphasis on &lt;em&gt;community&lt;/em&gt; center:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Harsh’s goals for the Hall Library differed from those of white librarians at the beginning of her tenure: while library science literature often focused on the education of individual patrons, the Hall Library’s large displays, publicized debates, and use of space for community groups pointed to education as a community endeavor. (235)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt characterizes Harsh’s work as “a pioneering approach to the interconnection between social epistemology and community engagement in the library, which was made possible by her hard work and also through the Hall Library’s unique temporal and physical location” (235)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, really, really like this nod to the conditions of possibility, but also to the intervention and labor of Harsh herself. (Certainly one works within history not of one’s own making—but one must really &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; as well, and it’s important to give credit to those who do rather than make it seem inevitable that someone would have.) What are the current conditions of possibility for libraries, and what can/can’t we help bring about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Harsh adapted her visions in different ways through the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s. Her work and her approach to libraries’ role in the community significantly influenced the development of community librarianship as well as African American education and cultural studies. (235)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt says that two major themes of Harsh’s career are (1) insistence for her (African American) patrons to learn African American history (often not taught in schools at the time {==to me, often &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not taught adequately==}) and (2) belief in education as way of patrons improving their lives. (236)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm. Seems like the second would clearly link up with Progressive, particularly class-based “improvement” narratives, with education as an engine for improvement (not that this link is wrong, clearly, but I also wonder whether/how labor was acknowledged). How different was the focus on history to common Progressive narratives, which might have been more future-focused?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt discusses historical specificities of class, education, socio-economic factors of Northern Migration (not named as such in this paragraph) and of Chicago Black Renaissance, which she describes as “a major social and cultural movement that continued the ideas of the Harlem Renaissance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Historian Anne Meis Knupfer, who studies women’s participation in Bronzeville during this period, defines the Chicago Black Renaissance as a movement characterized by support of and interest in the arts, the growth of interest in the world-wide ideas and views of Africans and African Americans, and social activism. These ideas were echoed in the goals Harsh espoused for the Hall Library, with her Special Research Collection that encouraged study of African and African American topics and the programming she began that stressed ideals of democracy and community education. The Hall Library was one of the foci of the Chicago Black Renaissance, and Harsh may have inspired one of its central tenets: large community educational gatherings. (237)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fascinated by what these “large community educational gatherings” were like. Church revivals, but for history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Harsh’s dynamic strategy to connect her research collection to community outreach is in dramatic contrast to the activities of other African American libraries at the time. (239)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt discusses difficulties facing most African American libraries at the time: funding during Great Depression, struggle to collect books of interest to community patrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Harsh’s strategies: “she authored annual reports that both boasted of the use of the special collection and requested more money to purchase books” (240).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Wright used collection, Langston Hughes praised it &amp;amp; Hall librarians in a &lt;em&gt;Chicago Defender&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Book Review and Lecture Forum (BRLF) was a twice-monthly meeting where Bronzeville residents gathered to hear a book review or lecture given by another community member. Presentations were always followed by a discussion. (240)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was the criteria for presenting? Did you need to be “distinguished” in some way? Apparently ranged across fiction, nonfiction, and current topics. Zora Neale Hurston, Langston Hughes, Horace Cayton, and St. Clair Drake all discussed their current works in the 1930s. (240)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brought wide range of speakers, even when perhaps risky: “In 1939, for example, speakers from the Republican, Democratic, Socialist, Prohibition, and Communist parties each discussed their political philosophies with the Hall audience.” (241)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bronzeville patrons were given a safe place in the Hall Library to debate these questions at a time when African Americans who struggled for expanded rights or sought information on un-American politics could have been in a precarious situation with the Hall Library’s protection. (241)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Really intrigued by this idea of library as a protective space!&lt;/strong&gt; This seems importantly different from, even counter to, a simple Habermasian account of the “public sphere” as a non-differentiated space. (Still need to re-read some of dude’s work so I know whether I’m knocking him on account of less-discerning supporters or if he really doesn’t complicate his thought sufficiently to address American situations—or even to German ones, whose complications he might well hollow out in an overly simple narrative of economic interests.) Is this more like a Michael Warner counterpublic? Was it a little more like Vorris Nunley’s “hush harbor”? What were the conditions of participation? How did Harsh &amp;amp; the other participants manage to secure this status of the forums as such an open-minded space? It seems radically different from strains of Progressive thinking that can be very paternalistic and instead like they might have been arguing for a very pluralistic understanding of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List of wide variety of organizations and events; exhibits, programs, book lists; classes on foreign languages, public speaking, social psychology (p 241-2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aha: Harsh reached out to local churches, local papers, community groups in various ways, all “part of a coordinated plan of community involvement.” (242)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harsh also reported lightly on the content, primarily focusing on attendance and number of events writing annual reports. (242-3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, LIS generally focused on adult education as a solitary, individuated process for each patron: “Library science literature during the late 1920s and early 1930s echoed ALA president Judson Jennings’s insistence that libraries focus on books and on individual patrons.” (243)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder why Jennings focused so heavily on individuated patrons. What role did programming play in this vision of libraries from ALA? How were communities envisioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt characterizes Jennings’ view as “top-down” vs the discussions sessions Harsh promoted that seem to build from the knowledge already present in the community {==me: if not necessarily in each individual patron==}. (243-4) Although doesn’t use the Freireian terms, seems to cast Jennings as banking model, whereas Harsh seems much closer to liberation pedagogy model. Not sure if it’s quite problem-posing model, though. Would have to know how the discussions were conducted, I imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt points out that Harsh’s forums presaged Alvin Johnson’s calls for lectures, forums, and reading clubs in &lt;em&gt;The Public Library: A People’s University&lt;/em&gt; by five years. (244)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1940s had increasing racial targeting of African Americans in Chicago, in part because of white fears correlated to greatly rising African American population in Chicago (245). During war, their library’s “programming often emphasized politics through the lens of race and color, despite the threat of possible sedition charges for those who challenged too fiercely the current state of the country” (246). Programming around how the US was failing to live up to democracy for everyone, plus other “political, social, and economic problems” (246).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Hall Library also advocated the idea of equal rights through promotion of new books in its collection. For example, in 1943, in a column in the &lt;em&gt;Chicago Sunday Bee&lt;/em&gt; about World War II fiction, Harsh and librarian Annie Allen wrote that books could help readers, especially Bronzeville readers, envision a democratic and just postwar society. Therefore, they explained, they selected books that advocated a peace that would recognize “the essential dignity of every human being regardless of race, cree, or color and bring to full realization the true meaning of a democratic world.” (246)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not clear from this whether these “books” were mostly nonfiction or also fiction, and therefore how the librarians envisioned the relationship between fiction and imagining a just world. However, the idea of reading assisting in imagining a more just world links up profoundly with a lot of cultural studies, Afrofuturist, etc. notions of reading as an intervention in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-war lots of how-to education, plus discussions of full employment for war workers and opportunities for veterans (247).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with other community institutions, i.e. cast of a popular radio show called &lt;em&gt;Destination Freedom&lt;/em&gt; performed at the library, including dramatic reading of Langston Hughes’s “Freedom Train,” concert of other songs, mural displayed, etc. (247)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arna Bontemps wrote that the Hall Library’s staff seeks to “consolidate the advantages of democracy for the benefit of all those who can be reached” (247-8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s such a great phrase, “consolidate the advantages of democracy!!!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 1940s and early 1950s Harsh had increasing frustration with outreach—she asserted that the new migrants northward from the South were unfamiliar with using libraries as a result of their being unavailable to African American in the South (249).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Community-centered library outreach movement is not attributed to her [Vivian Harsh] in any way (250-1). Yet clearly Burt’s article shows that Harsh did lots of programming centered on her community, involving them in it profoundly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burt sees both conditions of possibility (including contemporaneous Chicago Black Renaissance and “the fact that the Hall Library was a part of a large northern urban public library system that supported her or benignly ignored her at other times”) and Harsh’s own gifts and assessment of community needs as reasons why Harsh succeeded (251).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/burt-vivian-harsh-adult-ed-librarys-role-as-community-center-2009/&quot;&gt;Burt, Laura. &amp;ldquo;Vivian Harsh Adult Ed Library&#39;s Role as Community Center.&amp;rdquo; 2009.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Ryan P. Randall at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook&quot;&gt;Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook&lt;/a&gt; on May 14, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crumpton and Bird. <i>Handbook for Community College Librarians.</i> 2013.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/crumpton-and-bird-handbook-for-community-college-librarians-2013/" />
  <id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/crumpton-and-bird-handbook-for-community-college-librarians-2013</id>
  <published>2016-05-11T14:31:28-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-11T14:31:28-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
    <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Link:&lt;br /&gt;
Crumpton, Michael A. and Nora J. Bird. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Handbook for Community College Librarians.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/805057822&quot;&gt;WorldCat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-information-literacy&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: Information Literacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information literacy concept arguably goes back to at least as 1880s, with Justin Winsor (first president of ALA) and William Frederick Poole (first director of Chicago PL) both “advocated free libraries on the basis of educating the masses and instilling a desire for self-culture or self-education, especially in those who had newly immigrated to the United States” (p. 39).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1960s information literacy was called “bibliographic instruction” or just “BI.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evan Farber at Earlham College in Indiana developed one of the first for-credit library instruction courses in the US in 1974. This program used face-to-face, synchronous approach because the staff-to-student ratio worked out. Miriam Dudley advocated for asynchronous with workbooks/handouts, an approach favored by larger institutions.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fngk&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fngk&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As books are no longer the anticipated format for carrying information, “bibliographic” seems increasingly anachronous. Paul Zurkowski is generally credited with the phrase “information literacy,” from a 1974 white paper for the U.S. National Commission on Libraries and Information Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some college systems use “information fluency” or “information competence” term, so it’s worth being aware of from transfer students. (p. 40)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Other Literacies” sidebar details:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;computer literacy (technical literacy)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;content literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;digital literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ICT (information communication technology) literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information competency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information fluency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;media literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;media-information literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transition literacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transliteracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACRL issued &lt;em&gt;Information Literacy Competency Standards for Higher Education&lt;/em&gt; in 2000, an update of 1987’s Model Statement of Objectives for Academic Bibliographic Instruction. ACRL’s Community and Junior College Section hasn’t made any statements about what should be considered standard at these institutions. (p. 43)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a small unpublished survey that the authors conducted, responses from 50 community college libraries indicated that only 50 percent had an institution-wide definition of an information-literate student, and only between 10 percent and 20 percent had information literacy initiatives built into the institution’s mission or strategic plan. This shows that information literacy is still library-centric and has not become a priority for educational institutions in general. (p. 44)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. So when students transfer from a place that does not have these standards to one that does, do they have to re-take the classes or otherwise demonstrate that they meet these requirements? How much does this vary between accrediting regions and institutions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion of critical literacy, Paulo Freire, Troy Swanson and David Patterson on page 45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;christine-bruces-frames--lenses-for-information-literacy&quot;&gt;Christine Bruce’s Frames / Lenses for Information Literacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors assert that these are presented as somewhat equal possible approaches, with Bruce saying that adopting a particular lens alters our perception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As we change the lens, the picture of information, content, instruction learning, curriculum, assessment, and information literacy itself changes. Each view has value, but when we limit ourselves to a particular one, we can be less than relevant to some students and their curricular contexts. (45)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Content is King&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information as commodity that can be transmitted, librarian as expert. Once students gain knowledge of how library works, context isn’t important. (45)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Competency is Permanent&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills seem to be the focus, rather than content. Librarian focuses on teaching skills, as they persist across sets of resources. Instruction design = figuring out which skills are needed. (45)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Learning Readiness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information is subjective for each student, and both instuction and assessment are highly contextual. (46)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Personal Relevance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information transformational when valuable for learner. Librarian presents scenarios and is motivational. Assessment best when viewing finished presentations that integrate found information (presumably papers, posters, or speeches rather than smaller worksheets or quizzes?). (46)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Social Impact&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information resides in social or disciplinary norms. (Is this genre theory or something more like sociology?) “Information literacy is about shaping informed societal members.” (46)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lens: Relational Approach to Information and Learning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Widest view of information as objective, subjective, or transformational. Seems most #critlib?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The content of instruction would include critiquing a wide variety of sources and examining the student’s own values in relation to that information. […] The curriculum allows the student to become self-aware of methods for critical assessment. The transformation of the student’s thinking is the focus of assessment.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information literacy seems conceived of as applying to the broadest range of situations, rather than primarily having a particular scope or focus. (46)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A full information literacy program, then, is looked at through these lenses at each of the constituencies that make up a college community. (47)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So although these lenses seem to be somewhat contradictory, they’re presented as instead being complementary? This is kinda confusing. Maybe I should try to ILL the Bruce and give it a read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors advocate collaborating with faculty experts to make contextualized information literacy instruction. (48)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As the relational approach lens indications, the most flexible information skills can be transformational and can last a lifetime (Bruce 2008). (48)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors imply link between fact that information literacy is contextual and difficulty of quantifiable measurement of whether an information literacy class helps a student attain particular, often narrowly defined, goals. (49)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors assert that library instruction should assess:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Effect on student learning&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Quality of the instruction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Appropriateness of the content covered (49)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors reiterate the tension between customizing class instruction (which can be better for students, particularly more advanced who need refinement rather than introduction of concepts) and quantitative assessment strategies. (50)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-instructional-design&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Instructional Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M. David Merrill suggests four phases of instructional design: activation, demonstration, application, and integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In information literacy instruction, an example would involve these steps: how to provide information, explaining how to access information, discussion of how to make information comparisons or evaluate resources, and then, perhaps, the proper use of the information obtained. (55)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview of learning styles, via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.learningstylesonline.com&quot;&gt;Learning Styles Online&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;visual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aural&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kinesthetic (57)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interactive / social&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;print / logical (according to authors, many community college students weren’t successful with this mode, despite it being the most common form of education)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;haptic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;olfactory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;solitary (57-8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Kolb’s four-stage learning cycle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;concrete experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reflective observation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abstract conceptualization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;active experimentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructional learning objectives to keep in mind, per Morrison, Ross, and Kemp 2004:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of this instruction?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can learners demonstrate their understanding of the material?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can you assess whether learners mastered the content?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What specific content and performance are expected as a result of the instruction? (58)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of moving between different learning styles with different methods of instruction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a lecture (abstract) on evaluating resources could also include a demonstration (concrete) with some practice time built in (active) and finally a write-up of the experience (reflective) (59)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dooley, Linder, and Dooley have written &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/57316610&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advanced Methods in Distance Education&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where they claim that successful distance education learning requires six competencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understanding adult learning theory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having the technical knowledge needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knowing how the instruction is designed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relating to communication skills in a virtual environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using graphic design to support learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;administrative issues (60)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADDIE instructional design model, originally developed by Florida State University:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analysis: identify instructional need or problem, address it by establishing instructional goals/objectives, analyze learning environment &amp;amp; learner’s existing knowledge and skill sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design: “learning objectives, assessment instruments, exercises, content, subject matter analysis, lesson planning, and media selection are developed and strategically planned” Also includes consultation with content instructors about possible assignments and how learning objectives can be assessed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development: Instruction designers &amp;amp; developers create and assign content materials selected earlier, including programmers developing and/or integrating technologies as necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementation: Develop procedures for training both the instructors and the learners. Instructor training “should cover the course curriculum, learning outcomes, method of delivery, and testing procedures”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluation:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Formative evaluation in each step of the ADDIE process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Summative evaluation includes tests designed for specific criteria / referenced items, also giving opportunities for user feedback (62)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interesting-other-bits&quot;&gt;Interesting Other Bits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Sheril Hook’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://crl.acrl.org/content/73/1/7.full.pdf+html&quot;&gt;“Impact? What Three Years of Research Tell Us about Library Instruction”&lt;/a&gt; she writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe we must continue to study information literacy and the most effective ways of teaching and share our findings through publication. We especially need more conceptual pieces that provide a theoretical framework in which to think about information literacy, and we should be looking beyond our borders in order to learn from others. (10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chapter-5--6-interesting-bibliography-bits&quot;&gt;Chapter 5 &amp;amp; 6 Interesting bibliography bits:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bruce, Christine. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/243601790&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Informed Learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 2008.&lt;br /&gt;
Cook and Sittler, editors. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/213384801&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Practical Pedagogy for Library Instructors: 17 Innovative Strategies to Improve Student Learning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 2008.  &lt;br /&gt;
Dooley, LInder, and Dooley.&lt;br /&gt;
Hook, Sheril. &lt;a href=&quot;http://crl.acrl.org/content/73/1/7.full.pdf+html&quot;&gt;“Impact? What Three Years of Research Tell Us about Library Instruction.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;College &amp;amp; Research Libraries&lt;/em&gt; 73.1, 2012.&lt;br /&gt;
Nahl, Diane and Dania Bilal. 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/163593073&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Information and Emotion: The Emergent Affective Paradigm in Information Behavior Research and Theory.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Roselle, Ann. “Community College Students.” in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/841199102&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Information Literacy Instruction that Works: a Guide to Teaching by Discipline and Student Population.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, ed. Patrick Ragains. 2013. &lt;br /&gt;
Swanson, Troy A. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/438935734&quot;&gt;“Applying a Critical Pedagogical Perspective to Information Literacy Standards.”&lt;/a&gt; (2004). &lt;br /&gt;
“. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/362135641&quot;&gt;“A Radical Step: Implementing a Critical Information Literacy Model.”&lt;/a&gt; (2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fngk&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Both of these history tidbits come from Grassian and Kaplowitz 2009, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/45575553&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Information literacy instruction: Theory and Practice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fngk&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/crumpton-and-bird-handbook-for-community-college-librarians-2013/&quot;&gt;Crumpton and Bird. &lt;i&gt;Handbook for Community College Librarians.&lt;/i&gt; 2013.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Ryan P. Randall at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook&quot;&gt;Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook&lt;/a&gt; on May 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Greer, Hess, and Kraemer. &ldquo;The Librarian Leading the Machine: a Reassessment of Library Instruction Methods.&rdquo; 2016.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/greer-hess-and-kraemers-the-librarian-leading-the-machine/" />
  <id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/greer-hess-and-kraemers-the-librarian-leading-the-machine</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T00:10:25-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T00:10:25-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
    <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Link (Open Access) :&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/6032308716&quot;&gt;WorldCat&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;http://crl.acrl.org/content/77/3/286&quot;&gt;College &amp;amp; Research Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This study specifically considers whether online information literacy instruction in an otherwise face-to-face course is effective in helping students achieve desired learning outcomes. (p. 286)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Oakland University, they have library instruction integrated into every section of Writing 160: Composition II. Presumably this comes after Composition I, and is required by all students. Is this how we’d want to target our in-depth research, to something like English 102 here? Do they do any outreach/basic instruction for a Composition I at OU, something analogous to our CWID 101?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They offer hybrid format: one hour of face-to-face instruction with an online module; also parallel of virtual lessons for online-only classes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on liaison roles for full-time meant that part-time taught all WRT 160 info lit sessions, which overloaded part-time folks, quickly needed to reassess strategy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question for present study, updated from 2005 since online instruction conditions of possibility very different from now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does the delivery format of information literacy instruction in face-to-face course sections affect attainment of student learning outcomes? (p. 287)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference Dewald 199 study of effective online learning objects for information literacy learning: internet gives unique opportunities for knowledge acquisition when coupled with sound instruction pedagogy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blummer developed a three-tiered hierarchy for librarians to consider when evaluating effectiveness of online learning objects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clark and Mayer cite the ability to provide immediate feedback as an essential best practice in e-learning instructional design,23 and studies on the use of feedback in online library instruction have illustrated that in-lesson feedback encourages students to engage in and deepen their learning. (p. 289)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For instance, Lindsay, Cummings, and Johnson examined the impact of placing online learning objects at various points in the research process where students fail or encounter difficulty. They found that, by locating resources in the context of these various library services, the use of the library’s online learning resources increased.31 So, as the use of course management systems has grown, “point-of-need” more often means embedded within the LMS. (p. 290)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, possibly produce embeddable instruction in smaller bits, asking instructors to place them not at all a single point, but rather that they are put closest to “point of need” within the course? How would this work for CWID or ENG 102? Would we break it more into CWID = intro to library as a resource &amp;amp; ENG 102 = focus on research &amp;amp; critical info lit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mention limitations of pre- and posttests, of multiple choice, and true-or-false questions, but unclear to me whether authors are suggesting approaches that would be preferable or sort of implying that more approaches need to be developed. They do clearly value figuring out ways to assess affective dimension of learning&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:soc&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:soc&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and suggest that using multiple years of assessment data is better than just using one. (p. 290-291)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of the Committee on Instruction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;met with faculty from the Writing and Rhetoric Department to reexamine the goals for WRT 160 library instruction from the writing department’s standpoint. Taking these needs into account, COI then held a series of meetings with all the librarians to reevaluate and reestablish the library’s goals and objectives for the WRT 160 classes. In the course of these meetings, the library faculty identified two goals for WRT 160 library instruction aimed at building students’ research and critical thinking skills: 1) students will learn the importance of using an effective search strategy; and 2) students will gain an understanding of the value of resource evaluation. Under each of these goals, the faculty then defined comprehensive yet realistic student learning outcomes around which the WRT 160 library content would be built (see appendix A for the full list of student learning outcomes).” (p. 291)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting way of phrasing the two broad goals. Neither specifically mentions the &lt;em&gt;library&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;search process&lt;/em&gt;, focusing instead on search as a strategy (does this iterate? is it taught as contextual? I’ll have look at Ye Olde Appendixe) and on resource evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Split some of their content modules, deciding which were better done in-person &amp;amp; which done face-to-face:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Content Module&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Delivery Method&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Effective keyword brainstorming&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;face-to-face&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Best practices for database searches&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;face-to-face&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;How to read, interpret, and evaluate database results&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;face-to-face&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;How to access books and articles that you find&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;face-to-face&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Types of information sources and their uses&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;online via LMS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Evaluating resources&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;online via LMS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Finding specific items (“known item searching”)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;online via LMS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting. I’d expect all of these except for “how to access books and articles that you find,” which I’d have imagined would be done online. Or do they sort of introduce that via the known item search, then go further in depth during the face-to-face session, where they can talk more about it with whatever sources students actually find? I’d want to make a video for students for each, so they can be reminded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They now share a library instruction outline for face-to-face things to standardize content while allowing for different approaches to delivery, which we already do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had been spending &lt;em&gt;two hours face-to-face&lt;/em&gt; with each WRT 160 section! We sometimes just get 30 minutes! No wonder ours occasionally feel rushed &amp;amp; shallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of significant note is the fact that, where once the librarians required students to complete the online library content before their classes came to the library for the face-to-face session, this curricular overhaul allowed the librarians to complete in-class instruction and then direct students to the LMS at the end of the session. This switch has improved understanding of the process and has increased completion rates. (p. 292)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So do they now meet first, then have sort of follow-up homework? Is the “homework” automatically evaluated by the LMS (quiz or similar)? (Oh, according to p. 293, they can retake the final exam online, so I guess that’s a sort of automatic evaluation.) What explains the increased completion rate? Is it affective (students feel more invested in or more comfortable with material after associating it with a human)? Is it something about the scaffolding of material? By how much did the completion rate increase?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, accompanying these changes was a wholly new approach to the assessment of WRT 160 library instruction. Instead of the long-standing pre-/posttest approach, the overhaul team developed a new library final exam with questions that directly correlate exam performance to student learning outcome attainment (see appendix B for alignment chart). At the end of the first year of implementation, curricular revisions were considered for every SLO with low attainment (which the team defined as fewer than 80 percent correct answers), resulting in some instructional changes and/or the clarification of some exam questions. (p. 292)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems really pragmatic and useful! It doesn’t necessarily isolate the library instruction as having been the variable that “effected” the change between before &amp;amp; after, but I’m not certain that is really necessary, since even pre-/posttest has the flaw of possibly just familiarizing test-takers with questions rather than truly ascribing the change to the instruction delivered. I also really appreciate the iterative nature of this approach to assessing whether instruction is working for the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve found use of quotation marks in a search to be an especially troublesome concept for students, both before this instructional overhaul and during it. (p. 294)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discuss 2015 ACRL &lt;em&gt;Framework for Information Literacy for Higher Education&lt;/em&gt;, saying that the online instructional model can be more thorough &amp;amp; more exploratory than might be possible in traditional face-to-face instruction. (p. 296-7)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ends by emphasizing role of librarian’s “pivotal role as the instructional designer” of information literacy instruction, i.e. warding off interpretation of the study as suggesting that librarians can somehow just make any ‘ol online modules and call it a day. (p. 297)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-a&quot;&gt;Appendix A&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t use CRAAP. Instead their evaluations are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;authority, currency, relevancy, accuracy, objectivity, and appropriateness to their level of research (298)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do they discuss/present “objectivity”? To me, there’s a big difference between discussing whether a source performs objectivity (e.g. as a marker of genre/discourse, or as aspirational, recognizing that bias is omnipresent but attempting to minimize its effects on this piece of writing) and whether something &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; objective. How much of this question of objectivity gets handed over to the WRT instructor? Did the writing instructors request “objectivity” or was this a librarian-led component of evaluation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:soc&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Here they refer to Schroeder and Cahoy’s definition, which is apparently and individual’s “attitudes, emotions, interests, motivation, self-efficacy, and values.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:soc&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/greer-hess-and-kraemers-the-librarian-leading-the-machine/&quot;&gt;Greer, Hess, and Kraemer. &amp;ldquo;The Librarian Leading the Machine: a Reassessment of Library Instruction Methods.&amp;rdquo; 2016.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Ryan P. Randall at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook&quot;&gt;Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/introduction/" />
  <id>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/introduction</id>
  <published>2016-04-30T13:46:21-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-30T13:46:21-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan P. Randall</name>
    <uri>http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Just like with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ryanpatrickrandall.com&quot;&gt;my main site&lt;/a&gt;, I’ll start this off with a song:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mj&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mj&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Uj3zitETs4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the beginning of an attempt at an &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/about&quot;&gt;open humanities research notebook&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve realized that for posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ryanpatrickrandall.com&quot;&gt;my regular site / blog&lt;/a&gt; I feel a need to wrap things up tidily, so I wanted a different space to corral things that are more in-process. I may go back and cherry-pick the reading posts from my “Info Fluxus” blog and add them here retrospectively…we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As librarians—and more fundamentally, as thinkers—it would probably behoove us to show the process of thoughts as they grow and evolve. So here’s a humble attempt to do that more openly. I hope you’ll consider doing something similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mj&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The more I think about it, the more I like the tension between Michael Jackson’s lyrics and the optimism of starting a new site. Research and making often has an element of tension for me, an edge I can hear some of in this song’s post-disco / anxious trouble funk groove. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mj&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook/2016/introduction/&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Ryan P. Randall at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan-p-randall.github.io/research-notebook&quot;&gt;Ryan P. Randall ∴ Research Notebook&lt;/a&gt; on April 30, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
